[Music]
[âm nhạc]
How to
báo hiếu thế nào cho
properly show filial piety. Dear fellow practitioners, lay people
đúng Kính thưa quý đạo hữu người tại gia
show filial piety to their parents by giving them
chúng ta báo hiếu cha mẹ bằng cách cho
clothes, food, and material possessions. This creates a karmic connection that allows us
cha mẹ quần áo đồ ăn vật thực thì duyên
to meet again in many lifetimes.
gặp lại trong nhiều kiếp giữa mình và
When
cha mẹ cũng là quần áo vật thực khi cha
our parents pass away, they are
mẹ mình mất đi thì cha mẹ theo nghiệp
reborn according to their karma. We cannot
lực của cha mẹ mà tái sinh mình không
help them immediately in this life, but they
giúp gì được ngay trong hiện tại cha mẹ
may be happy and warm
mình có thể rất vui vẻ với mình ấm áp
towards us. This is love, so that in the next life we ​​may meet
với mình đó là ái để kiếp sau có thể gặp
again and love each other. But if we
lại nhau cũng yêu thương nhau Nhưng nếu
kill living beings together and
cùng nhau sát mạng chúng sinh cùng nhau
commit evil deeds together, we will meet again to repay the karmic consequences in the
làm việc ác thì sẽ gặp nhau trả quả báo
next life, and we will also suffer.
kiếp sau gặp lại nhau cũng sẽ khổ
As for those who have renounced the world and become monks or nuns,
đau còn đối với người xuất gia tu đạo
if their hearts lack filial piety, they cannot become monks or
Nếu tâm người không có hiếu thì không
nuns. Therefore, one must have filial piety to become a monk or nun. And if they are filial, they will be
xuất gia Bởi vậy phải có hiếu thì mới
filial to the very
xuất gia mà đã Hiếu thì họ hiếu đến tận
end, and they will become monks or nuns to cultivate and attain enlightenment.
cùng thì họ sẽ xuất gia tu tập thành đạo
If a monk or nun does not reach the end of their practice and gives up along the way—that is,
Nếu trường hợp người xuất gia không tu
they cannot endure and cultivate to attain
sẽ bỏ cuộc Tức là mình không thể nhẫn
enlightenment—then during their
lại tu hành thành đạo thì trong thời
time as monks or nuns, they have guided their parents
gian Họ xuất gia họ đã cho cha mẹ hướng
towards the Three Jewels. That person still has a filial duty. When they become monks or nuns, their parents' hearts are directed towards the
về nơi tam bảo người đó vẫn có phần Hiếu
Three Jewels.
mình đi xuất gia cha mẹ Hướng Tâm về với
Whether one has an evil or a good heart, for example, Mrs.
đạo dù là ác tâm hay Thiện Tâm ví như bà
Thanh De. She hated Buddhism, but
Thanh Đề Bà ấy rất ghét đạo Phật nhưng
in the end, when Venerable Moggallana
cuối cùng khi ngài Mục Kiều Liên Tu
attained enlightenment, he still saved her because she still
thành đạo thì vẫn cứu được bà vì bà vẫn
loved him. Since he was still
ái ngài Mục Kiều Liên mà ngài còn ở
within the Dharma, she also had the karmic connection to enter the
trong giáo pháp nên bà cũng có duyên vào
Dharma to find her son. Therefore,
trong giáo pháp để tìm con bà cho nên
each sentient being can save those sentient beings who have a karmic connection
mỗi chúng sinh đều độ được những chúng
with them when practicing.
sinh có hữu duyên với mình khi tu tập
This karmic connection is not considered evil or good.
Hữu Duyên này không tính là ác hay Thiện
Therefore, the karmic connection is the cause and effect for parents to enter the
Bởi vậy xuất là nhân duyên để cha mẹ vào
Three Jewels, to hear and learn the
trong tam bảo cha mẹ được nghe học phật
Dharma, to abandon evil, to do good, and to be liberated from the cycle of reincarnation.
pháp bỏ ác làm lành giải thoát luân hồi
Even if we feed our parents
cho dù ở thế gian chúng ta cho cha mẹ ăn
a lot in this world, it is only to nourish their
thật nhiều đi nữa thì cũng chỉ là nuôi
lives and create karma, and then they will continue to wander
mạng sống để tạo nghiệp rồi Trôi lăn
in the cycle of reincarnation.
Trong luân hồi
But if we let our parents
thôi nhưng nếu chúng ta để cho cha mẹ
turn towards the Three Jewels, to love their children, and then come
hướng về nơi tam bảo yêu quý con rồi đến
to the Three Jewels, even if it's just a
với tam bảo cho dù cha mẹ chỉ một niệm
tiny thought in the Dharma, yes, there is
mảy may trong Phật pháp Ừ đúng là có
cause and effect. Even such a small thought can lead
nhân quả chỉ một niệm nhỏ như thế cũng
them through many lifetimes to enter the
nhiều đời nhiều kiếp họ được vào trong
Three Jewels, practice the Dharma, and be
tam bảo thực hành Giáo Pháp được giải
liberated. Therefore, those who practice the Dharma and become monks or nuns are the
thoát cho nên người tu đạo xuất gia là
ones who bring about the karmic connection
người đưa lại nhân duyên tu tập giải
for their parents to practice and attain liberation.
thoát cho cha mẹ mình thái tử Tất Đạt Đa
When King Suddhodana left the city to become a monk, he
khi vượt thành xuất gia vua Tịnh Phạn
fainted and regained consciousness for seven days. However,
ngất đi tỉnh lại trong 7 ngày nhưng sau
after the prince attained Buddhahood, he helped
khi thái tử Tu thành Phật đã độ cho bố
his father achieve enlightenment and liberation before his death.
mình trước lúc chết Đạt Đạo quả giải
Therefore, the filial piety of a monk towards his
thoát Vì vậy Hiếu của người xuất gia đối
parents is far greater than the filial
thoát luân hồi cho cha mẹ cao hơn rất
piety of a lay person, which
nhiều lần so với Hiếu của người tại gia
only provides food and
là chỉ có cơm ăn áo
clothing. The karmic connection of a monk who brings the
mặc duyên của người tu đạo mang giáo
Buddha's teachings to save sentient beings is that
pháp của Phật cứu độ quần sinh thì duyên
their parents also
của người mẹ người cha của họ cũng được
benefit from the care they receive. We
lợi ích từ tất cả mọi người chăm sóc
must believe that when a child becomes a
chúng ta phải tin rằng có người con xuất
monk and strives for the benefit of sentient beings, their
gia tu hành nỗ lực vì chúng sinh thì cha
parents will surely have the karmic connection to be
mẹ ắt sẽ có nhân duyên được người khác
cared for by others; this is the karmic reward of a
chăm sóc đó chính là phước báo của người
monk. As lay Buddhists, we
tu hành Người Phật tử tại gia chúng ta
repay our parents' kindness by
báo đáp ân đức cho cha mẹ là mình cũng
finding ways to guide them
phải tìm mọi cách để hướng cho cha mẹ
towards the Buddha's teachings so that they, through many
mình nương về Phật pháp để cha mẹ nhiều
lifetimes and eons of practice, can escape the cycle of
đời nhiều Kiếp Tu Hành mà ra khỏi luân
reincarnation, not just the responsibility of providing food and
hồi chứ không chỉ là trách nhiệm mỗi cơm
clothing. Those disciples of the Buddha who have become monks and nuns,
mặc còn những người đệ tử Phật đã xuất
wholeheartedly seeking liberation, naturally
gia tu đạo một lòng cầu giải thoát họ tự
have the karmic connection to bring benefits and
có nhân duyên mang lại lợi ích Hiếu
filial piety to their parents. Becoming a monk is...  The
Thuận cho cha mẹ việc xuất gia là hiếu
highest form of filial piety is when parents are guided and supported, so that
đạo cao nhất Cha mẹ cần phải được độ thì
in many future lifetimes they will have the opportunity to guide and support
trong nhiều kiếp nữa họ cũng sẽ có duyên
their own parents.
độ cha mẹ của mình
[music]
[âm nhạc]